<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: djugl | Morethanseven]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/tags/djugl/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-20T21:07:19+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gareth Rushgrove]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DJUGL February]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/2010/02/11/djugl-february/"/>
    <updated>2010-02-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/2010/02/11/djugl-february</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The next Django User Group London is in two weeks time. You can register over on "Eventwax":http://londonpython.eventwax.com/djugl-february. So far we have "Brad":http://intranation.com talking with more speakers to be announced shortly. Hope to see a few people there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DJUGL December]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/2009/11/05/djugl-december/"/>
    <updated>2009-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/2009/11/05/djugl-december</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As mentioned at the last event I've taken over organising the Django User Group London event from Rob. Tickets are now available for the next event which is going to be on the 3rd of December at The Guardian offices in Kings Cross.</p>

<p>You can sign up on "eventwax":http://londonpython.eventwax.com/djugl-december</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Another chance to DJUGL]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/2009/08/31/another-chance-djugl/"/>
    <updated>2009-08-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/2009/08/31/another-chance-djugl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>"DJUGL":http://djugl.eventwax.com/djugllondon-python is back, the <em>monthly</em> Django meetup in London. I think the last few times have been as much about useful Python stuff as just using Django, and this time it's officially a bit more broad ranging. If you're in or around London on the 24th September then come along.</p>

<p>You can get more information on "Twitter":http://twitter.com/londonpython or by following "Rob":http://twitter.com/robertlofthouse/. But expect a few short talks, some interesting conversations and maybe some beer with other like minded developers.</p>

<p>I'm going to be talking about automating deployment of Python web applications. If you follow me on Twitter you'll have heard me rambling a little about some of what I've been up to, and some of the posts here give an insight into what I've been working on. But the short version is that several friends mentioned how difficult it could be to get a working Django application from a local machine to a production web server. And I though I better get down in script form my experiences of Django, WSGI applications and web server setup to make things easier.</p>

<p>I think this situation is partially caused by the success of the Django development server, and partially by people coming from a PHP background. In my PHP days I think I always wanted to know how Apache did it's think, so long ago jumped into anything and everything in httpd.conf from loading modules to virtual hosts. But not everyone does the same, and PHP does make simple deployments easy enough that you might get away without doing so. Rails went through the same problems and seems to be coming out the other side. I'm hoping that Django and Python is soon to be in the same position, where basic deployment is just a given.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Django Testing Presentation at DJUGL]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/2009/01/20/django-testing-presentation-djugl/"/>
    <updated>2009-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/2009/01/20/django-testing-presentation-djugl</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The second "Django User Group (DJUGL)":http://upcoming.yahoo.com/event/1463406 meeting was last night and was a great success as far as I could tell. Our boardroom at work was chock full of budding Django developers and interested parties - 70 people or so in all. Good work by Rob to get everything back on track at the start of the year and the next event is already planned for the back end of February so I hear. More news soon on the "mailing list":http://groups.google.com/group/django-london hopefully.</p>

<p>Rather unfortunately "Simon":http://simonwillison.net had to pull out at the last minute and I stepped in to do a quick 20 minutes or so talk on writing tests for your Django applications.</p>

<div style="width:425px;text-align:left" id="__ss_933741"><object style="margin:0px" width="425" height="355"><param name="movie" value="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=testingdjangoapps-1232444197115958-3&rel=0&stripped_title=testing-django-applications-presentation" /><param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"/><param name="allowScriptAccess" value="always"/><embed src="http://static.slideshare.net/swf/ssplayer2.swf?doc=testingdjangoapps-1232444197115958-3&rel=0&stripped_title=testing-django-applications-presentation" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="355"></embed></object></div>


<p>I was rather surprised that only about a third of the people coming along were using Django in some work related capacity, and when I asked who was writing tests for their code a few more hands went down. Very few of the people <em>not</em> using Django at work are writing tests which is unfortunate (and contrasts rather interestingly with my experiences of the Ruby community).</p>

<p>For a presentation done in less than a day while at work I felt it went OK. testing is a hard sell at the best of times and trying to talk to both those without experience of writing tests and at the same time trying to get in a few of the more interesting things we've done at work was maybe a bit of an ask.</p>

<p>It not being a blog post round here these days unless I include a link to GitHub I did mention a small project last night in the talk - "Django Test Extensions":http://github.com/garethr/django-test-extensions/. It's more just a collection of useful common testing code: additional assertions, custom test runners, etc. Thanks to "Ross":http://agileweb.org/ for the last minute patch with a couple of bug fixes as well.</p>

<p>The other two presentations went great. Andrew talking about the South migrations system and Aral talking about real world Google App Engine were both up my street of things I'm interested in. We have video of all the talks as well so hopefully that will make it out into the wild at some point once it's been edited.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
