<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: morbid | Morethanseven]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/tags/morbid/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-25T18:50:55+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gareth Rushgrove]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jabber, Erlang, Debugging. Things I'm playing with at the moment]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/2008/10/05/jabber-erlang-debugging-things-im-playing-with-at-/"/>
    <updated>2008-10-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/2008/10/05/jabber-erlang-debugging-things-im-playing-with-at-</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm busy experimenting with various blogging approaches at the moment, hence the short links I've been posting recently. Another type of post I thought I'd give a try to was the list of interesting things. I find this sort of thing strangely cathartic - if nothing else by writing down the things I'm thinking about I won't forget to spend time playing with them.</p>

<ul>
<li>I still need to play around some more with Jabber/XMPP. I tried a little time ago to install a server locally on my Mac with only some success. I've now got a load of linux virtual images handy which might make that easier. What I would really like to see is a dirt simple XMPP server that you can use for local development. Something like "Morbid":http://pypi.python.org/pypi/morbid/0.8.2. I'm just not sure I have the time to build one.</li>
<li>Which brings me on to virtualisation. I'm more convinced than ever that sand boxing different local environments is a good idea. I now have a stack of VMWare images set up for configuring.</li>
<li>It turns out "Yahoo used Erlang":http://blog.socklabs.com/cufp2008.html under the hood for some part of the new "Delicious":http://del.icio.us I'm still pretty interested in actually doing something with Erlang, though what I'm not yet sure. I've been kicking round an idea for ages involving logging which might fit the bill.</li>
<li>I talked at barcampbrighton recently about debugging tools for django (and more broadly any development environment) that you need once you have a reasonable sized team. I've been busy packaging some of the tools I mentioned. I'll either turn it into an article somewhere, multiple blog posts and/or hopefully get some code released on google code some time soon.</li>
<li>The "Sphinx":http://sphinx.pocoo.org/ documentation system used by Django for the "1.0 documentation":http://docs.djangoproject.com/en/dev/ is pretty nifty. I'm investigating it for use at work at the moment.</li>
<li>I've been a huge fan of Textile since I used Textpattern years ago for an earlier incarnation of this site. But recently I've had a few niggling issues around extensibility and slight differences in implementation. So I'm pondering using "ReStructuredText":http://docutils.sourceforge.net/rst.html for my writing duties. It appears to be more powerful, more flexible and inherently extensible.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
