<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gds | Morethanseven]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/tags/gds/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-20T20:18:02+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gareth Rushgrove]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Leaving GDS never easy]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/2014/07/20/leaving-gds-never-easy/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-20T20:10:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/2014/07/20/leaving-gds-never-easy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The following is the email I sent to lots of my colleagues at the
<a href="https://gds.blog.gov.uk/">Government Digital Service</a> last week.</em></p>

<p>So, after 3 rather exciting years I've decided to leave GDS.</p>

<p>That's surprisingly difficult to write if I'm honest.</p>

<p>I was part of the team that built and shipped the beta of <a href="https://www.gov.uk">GOV.UK</a>.
Since then I've worked across half of what has become GDS, equally
helping and frustrating (then hopefully helping) lots of you. I've
done a great deal and learnt even more, as well as collected arcane
knowledge about government infosec and the dark arts of procurement
along the way. I've done, and helped others do, work I wouldn't even
have thought possible (or maybe likely is the right word?) when I
started.</p>

<p>So why leave? For all the other things I do I'm basically a tool
builder. So I'm going off to work for <a href="http://puppetlabs.com">Puppet Labs</a> to build
infrastructure tools that don't suck. That sort of pretty specific
work is something that <em>should</em> be done outside government in my
opinion. I'm a pretty firm believer in "government should only do what
only government can do" (<a href="https://www.gov.uk/design-principles#second">design principle number 2</a> for those that
haven't memorised them yet). And if I'm honest, focusing on something
smaller than fixing a country's civic infrastructure is appealing for
now.</p>

<p>I'll let you in on a secret; I didn't join what became GDS because of
the GOV.UK project. I joined to work with friends I'd not yet had the
chance to work with and to see the inside of a growing organisation
from the start. I remember <a href="http://twitter.com/tomskitomski">Tom Loosemore</a> promising me we'd be 200
people in 3 years! As far as anyone knows we're 650+ people. That's
about a person a day for 2 years. I'm absolutely not saying that came
without a cost, but for me being part of that that was part of the
point - so I can be a little accepting with hindsight.</p>

<p>For me, apart from all the short term things (side-note: this job now
has me thinking £10million is a small amount of money and 2 years is a
small amount of time) there is one big mission:</p>

<blockquote><p>Make government a sustainable part of the UK tech community</p></blockquote>

<p>That means in 10 years time experienced tech people from across the
country, as well as people straight from university, choosing to work
for government. Not just for some abstract and personal reason (though
that's fine too), but because it's a a genuinely interesting place to
work. That one's on us.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going fast in government]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/2013/02/17/going-fast-in-government/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-17T17:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/2013/02/17/going-fast-in-government</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a month ago I had the good fortune of speaking at the "London Web Performance":http://www.meetup.com/London-Web-Performance-Group/ meetup. This was one of the first talks I've done about our work at The Government Digital Service since the luanch of GOV.UK back in October. The topic was all about moving quickly in a large organisation (The UK Civil Service is about 450,000 people so I think it counts) and featured just a hand full of technical and organisational tricks we used.</p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="bc48ed2042c20130b322123138156909" data-ratio="1.33333333333333" src="http://www.morethanseven.net//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Shipping]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/2012/10/21/shipping/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-21T21:50:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/2012/10/21/shipping</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week we shipped "GOV.UK":https://www.gov.uk. Over the last year we've built a team to build a website. Now we're busy building a culture too. I've got so much that needs writing up about everything we've been up to. Hopefully I'll make a start in the next week or so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Her Majesty's Digital Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/2011/08/19/On-her-majestys-digital-service/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-19T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/2011/08/19/On-her-majestys-digital-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog post is mainly an excuse to use the pun in the title. It's also an opportunity to tell folks that don't already know I'll be starting a new job on Monday working for the UK Government. I'm going to be work for the "Government Digital Service":http://digital.cabinetoffice.gov.uk/, a new department tasked with a pretty wide range of sorting the Government out online.</p>

<p>The opportunity is huge. And when it came around I couldn't turn it down. I'm going to be working with a bunch of people I've "known":http://memespring.co.uk/ "and":http://nicepaul.com/ "respected":http://fberriman.com/ for a while, as well as other equally smart people. That means I'm going to be back in London again as well.</p>

<p>Hopefully I'll be able to talk lots about what we're up to. The groundwork for that has already been laid by the "alpha.gov":http://alpha.gov.uk team who have been blogging furiously about topics of interest.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
