<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vim | Morethanseven]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/tags/vim/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/"/>
  <updated>2013-12-26T18:51:05+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Gareth Rushgrove]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim With Ruby Support Using Homebrew]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.morethanseven.net/2011/07/31/Vim-with-ruby-support-using-homebrew/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-31T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.morethanseven.net/2011/07/31/Vim-with-ruby-support-using-homebrew</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've spend a bit of time this weekend cleaning, tidying and upgrading software on my mac. While doing that I got round to compiling my own Vim. I'd been meaning to do this for a while, I prefer using Vim in a terminal to using MacVim, and I like having access to things like "Command-T":http://www.vim.org/scripts/script.php?script_id=3025 which requires Ruby support which the inbuild version lacks.</p>

<p>Vim isn't in Homebrew, because Homebrew's policy is to not provide duplicates of already installed software. Enter "Homebrew Alt":https://github.com/adamv/homebrew-alt which provides formulas for anything not allowed by the homebrew policy. As luck would have it a "Vim Formula":https://github.com/adamv/homebrew-alt/blob/master/duplicates/vim.rb already exists. And installing from it couldn't be easier.</p>

<pre>brew install https://raw.github.com/adamv/homebrew-alt/master/duplicates/vim.rb</pre>


<p>As it turns out this failed the first time I ran it because I had an rvm installed Ruby on my path. I reset this to the system version and everything compiled fine.</p>

<pre>rvm use system</pre>


<p>Note also that it's really quite simple to use a different revision or different flags when compiling. Just download that file, modify it, serve it locally (say with a python one line web server) and point brew install at it. Next step, running off head for all the latest and greatest Vim features.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
